When the cold comes for you,
當你遭遇嚴寒侵襲時
the blood stops running to your limbs.
血液會停止流向四肢
It pools up inside to keep your organs warm.
它會流向軀干 保持臟器溫暖
My first love told me that.
這是我的初戀情人告訴我的
An offshore roughnecker he was. Tall and lean, and tough as whitleather.
他是個海上勞工 高高瘦瘦 體格強健
He'd say, "Ruthie, your smile keeps me warm."
他會說：“魯絲 你的微笑讓我溫暖
"So be sure to wear it till I'm home."
所以千萬要保持微笑 直到我回來”
- Let's go. - Right.
-好 我們走吧 -好
- Move it. - Okay.
-走起來 -好
Uh, yeah, that was some shit.
沒錯 那玩意兒很厲害
Next, the cold comes for your mind.
接著 嚴寒就會侵襲你的思想
And after that, your will.
然后是你的意志力
And yet still,
不過
the heart fights on.
你的心依然在抗爭
Ruth.
是魯絲
She says Wilford's up to something in the back.
她說威爾福德正在車尾搞什么勾當
♪ Ain't no sunshine when she's gone ♪
她走之后就沒了陽光
♪ It's not warm when she's away ♪
她不在時就沒了溫暖
♪ And she's always gone too long ♪
而她總是離開得太久
♪ Anytime she goes away ♪
每次她離開
Big day, friends.
朋友們 今天是大日子
- Big day, sir. - Everything's ready for the test.
確實是大日子 先生 測試需要的一切都準備好了
Dear, poor Dr. Headwood.
可憐的黑得伍德醫生 親愛的
How are you doing without our dear, poor Dr. Headwood?
你那可憐的丈夫 黑得伍德醫生去世后 你還好嗎
I feel he's still with us, sir.
我感覺他依然跟我們在一起 先生
Are you confident here, in his shoes as it were?
接手他以前的工作 你有信心嗎
Hundred percent.
絕對有 先生
Yes, how is this for the occasion? It's very, um, Manhattan Project.
對了 您看這身衣服行嗎  很有“曼哈頓計劃”的風范
Fine, fine.
挺好
Put down the lint brush and hand me my towel.
放下棉絨刷 把毛巾遞給我
Pardon me. We do have much to do.
我失陪了 我們有很多工作要做
Thank you.
謝謝
He left me too soon, my roughneck love.
我那位海上勞工戀人過早地離開了我
His rig went down with every man aboard.
他工作的鉆井平臺塌了 所有的人都沉入了海底
I know my smile kept him warm as he floated, all alone.
我知道在他獨自漂浮時 我的微笑讓他感到溫暖
Just as I know our hearts will be the last thing to go
我也知道 在威爾福德這列 1023節車廂組成的列車上
on Wilford's train.
我們的心將會是
1,023 cars long.
最后屈服的東西
She's, um, dehydrated, malnourished, her blood pressure's low.
她有脫水癥狀 營養不良 而且血壓很低
Hey. You wanna talk about what happened out there?
嘿 想不想談談 在外面發生的那件事
Yeah, when you two almost died.
想 你們倆差點就沒命了
No, when we kissed.
不是那個 是我們接吻的事
I got a baby on the way, and I made a promise to Zarah.
我馬上就要當爸爸了 而且我答應過扎拉
- I don't need to talk about it. - No, me either.
-我不需要談那件事 -好 我也不需要
Ben's got the data. Shall we see if it's been worth it?
本拿到數據了 要不要去看看 這番鬧騰是否值得
Yeah. Yes.
好的
I still don't get how it's possible to survive eight years out there.
我還是不明白 她怎么可能在外面生存八年
You freeze yourself in.
用冰把自己封在室內
Live off the residual power as the reactor cools.
隨著反應堆冷卻 靠剩余的電力維持生命
It's kind of genius if you ask me.
要我說 這辦法太有才了
It's not even why you went out there in the first place.
你當初出去 都不是為了找她
No.
沒錯
We have our results.
結果出來了
Guessing that grimace isn't just from the ribs.
我估計這表情 不光是因為你的肋骨疼吧
More of the same.
跟之前的差不多
Analysis shows location is warming,
分析顯示該區域正在變暖
but the trend isn't steep enough to be habitable yet.
但變化速度不夠快 暫時還不宜居住
How long are we talking, Ben?
那要等多久呢 本
- A century? - Give or take.
-一個世紀  -差不多吧
Well, that's O-for-five on this milk run.
已經是第五個點了 還是不行
Okay, that leaves one more location.
好吧 那就只剩最后一個地點了
Your Arabian warm spot.
阿拉伯的那個暖點
Yeah. From all the data we've collected so far,
對 從我們迄今為止 采集到的所有數據來看
it looks actually pretty promising.
那個地方實際上很有希望
Located here, Horn of Africa, southern Arabian Peninsula.
它位于這里 非洲之角 阿拉伯半島以南
We haven't enough food to get there.
本 我們的食物不夠了 撐不到那里的
- We've got another mouth to feed. - It's time to get our train back.
-現在我們又多了一張嘴 -該去奪回我們的列車了
We find them, reconnect to the train, we lead everybody to the new hot spot.
我們找到他們 重新連接列車 然后帶大家一起去新的暖點
I'm far less concerned with taking her, than keeping her.
跟奪回列車相比 我更擔心奪回后能否保住它
She's right. We're going back empty-handed.
她說得沒錯 我們這可是空手而歸啊
- No proof of New Eden.
沒有新伊甸園存在的證據
- No Melanie.
也沒有梅蘭妮
We're not empty-handed.
我們不是空手而歸
Far from it.
遠非如此
Hey.
嘿
Come on. Hey.
醒醒 嘿
Okay. No, it's okay. I got it.
好吧 別 沒事的 我能行
Hey, no, you're all right. Hey, you're all right.
嘿 別緊張 沒事的 一切都好
Look, you don't need the suit here. See?
聽著 在這里 不需要穿防護服 看到嗎
It's all right, yeah.
嗯 沒事了
Uh, hi.
你好
My name's Andre Layton.
我叫安德烈雷頓
We kind of met already, uh, fighting in the nuclear plant.
我們算是見過面了 在核電站時我們打了一架
You remember that? I'm sorry, do you speak English?
記得嗎 對不起 你會說英語嗎
Yeah?
會
Here.
給
Okay.
好
All right?
好點了
What's your name?
你叫什么名字
- Asha. - Asha.
-阿莎 -阿莎
Great.
很好
Don't worry, you're safe here.
別擔心 你在這里是安全的
No one's gonna hurt you, you're on Snowpiercer.
沒人會傷害你 你在雪國列車上
Snowpiercer?
雪國列車
Not unless we all are.
除非我們大家都在做夢
- The train survived? - Let me show you. Can you walk?
-那列車幸存下來了  -我帶你去看看吧 你能走嗎
Just up here.
就在上面
Who is that? You lost the privilege to ask questions.
-她是什么人  -你已經沒資格提問了
Oh, come on, Bess. Were they outside?
得了 貝絲 他們之前是在外面嗎
How's your head? Bet it hurts.
你的腦袋怎么樣 估計很疼吧
Not as bad as when you broke my nose.
沒你打斷我鼻梁骨時那么疼
Where's Mr. Wilford, the Great Engineer?
那個偉大的工程師威爾福德先生呢
Uh, yeah, we don't know. There's two trains now.
我們其實不知道 現在有兩列列車了
There's a woman in a cage.
樓下有一個女人被關在一間牢房里
It's a long, complicated story. You've got one too, and I wanna hear it,
這故事又長又復雜 你也有故事 我很想聽
but it's better to take one thing at a time right now, trust me.
不過 目前最好是 一次消化一件事 相信我
Why should I trust any of this?
我憑什么要相信這些
Welcome aboard, Asha.
歡迎登車 阿莎
Ten percent should give us a nice jolt. Nothing too lethal.
釋放10%應該就能引起震撼 卻不會致命
An appropriate test level, sir.
這個水平很適合測試 先生
And the decommissioned First Class cars
撤空的頭等車廂
should provide the necessary buffer from the EMP pulse.
應該能為電磁脈沖的沖擊 提供必要的緩沖
Well, let's hear her sing, Kevin.
好了 凱文 我們來聽它“一展歌喉”吧
Commence trial. Ten percent.
開始測試 釋放10%
Confirmed, ten percent.
確認 釋放10%
Initiate countdown.
開始倒計時
We're all clear.
都準備好了
Initiating countdown.
倒計時開始
Two minutes.
兩分鐘
Brought your little friend back.
我把你的小朋友帶回來了
Shouldn't we get out of here?
我們不是該離開這里嗎
I'd wager that it's a weapon.
我敢打賭那是某種武器
It's set in the very last car, right where the trains need to reconnect.
它設在最后一節車廂里 那是列車重新連接的地方
Are you sure it's not just a heater?
你確定不會只是一個加熱器嗎
- You all right? - Yes, thanks. I'm just cold.
-你沒事吧  -沒事 謝謝關心 我只是冷
That's why you can't be running around out there.
所以你不該在外面跑
We can't afford to lose you.
我們不能失去你
I'm no use to anyone hiding in a hole, am I?
要是整天躲在洞里 我還有什么用
And in five, four,
倒數五、四
It's all right.
沒事了
What was that?
剛才那是什么
Felt like some electrical wave went through me.
感覺像某種電波從我體內穿過
I think that was the thing.
我想這就是那個武器了
Well done, Kevin. Well done, crew.
干得漂亮 凱文 大家干得都漂亮
Yes!
太好了
I wanna remember this.
我想記住這一刻
it's a mean old world,
這個世界很無情
but with you in it,
但是有了你
it finally makes sense.
它終于有了意義
Lilah Junior,
小萊拉
will you marry me?
你愿意嫁給我嗎
Holy shit, that rock is huge!
老天啊 這顆鉆石真大
I know. It's actually crazy. It's probably the biggest diamond left in the world.
可不是 說來你可能不信 這可能是世上現存的最大的鉆石了
- All it cost was a pair of heavy socks. - Put it on me.
-只用一雙厚襪子就換來了 -快給我戴上
You gotta say yes first.
你得先說“我愿意”才行
Yes, yes.
我愿意
I didn't think anyone would love me after my parents died.
父母去世后 我以為不會再有人愛我了
I know, baby. I know.
我知道 寶貝 我知道
We have to tell Wilford.
我們得告訴威爾福德
Really?
不是吧
Yes. Out of respect.
是的 出于尊重
After you now.
除了你以外
Okay.
好吧
Lilah Junior and Mr. Osweiller are here to see you.
小萊拉和奧斯威勒先生來了 他們想見你
Ah, bring them.
帶他們進來
- He's wearing a tie. - Mmm?
他戴著領帶呢
My young denizens of the Nightcar.
我年輕的夜車居民們
- Could we have a word in private-- - We're getting married.
-我們能私下談談… -我們要結婚了
- What? - We wanted you to be the first to know.
-什么  -我們想第一個告訴您
LJ, my dear, what a surprise.
LJ 親愛的 這真是驚喜啊
Very wise to put such a nice ring on her finger, Mr. Osweiller.
給她戴上這么漂亮的戒指 是一項明智之舉 奧斯威勒先生
When was the last time we had a wedding?
我們有多久沒舉辦過婚禮了
This is quite the occasion.
這可是大事情
Perhaps just the occasion the train needs.
或許正是列車此刻所需要的
No, we're not expecting anything.
不 我們沒想大肆操辦
- We don't even-- - I am.
-我們甚至都不… -我想
And you should, my dear. Life's been so bloody dreary this leg.
你應該辦一場大婚禮 親愛的 人生的這一程太艱苦了
We'll give everyone a shift off.
我們會允許所有人都歇一個班次
Let's remind all the grumblers what unity looks like.
提醒一下那些抱怨的人 團結是什么樣子的
That we're all in this together, and loyalty is rewarded.
提醒他們我們是同一列列車上的 忠誠會得到回報
- What do you think?
你覺得怎么樣
- We could all use a little respite.
稍微歇口氣對大家有好處
- Maybe an extra ration or-- - Wonderful. Tomorrow then.
-或許可以多分一兩份口糧… -太好了 那就定在明天
Tomorrow?
明天
Yeah. Why not? No time for cold feet.
是呀 有何不可 沒時間臨陣退縮
We'll transform the Nightcar, LJ.
LJ 我們要讓夜車煥然一新
Or should I say, Mrs. Osweiller?
或者我該稱呼你為 “奧斯威勒太太”
Rolls off the tongue. I'm seeing red velvet, layers.
非常順口 我要用層層的紅色天鵝絨來布置
- You put the Cakemaker in Compost. - Then get him out. We're getting married.
-你把糕點師貶入堆肥區了 -那就把他弄出來 我們要舉辦婚禮
Get him a shower and anything he needs from the bakery, okay?
給他沖個澡 他做糕點需要什么 就去面包房拿 明白嗎
Thank you. Thank you.
謝謝
What the hell are you doing here?
你在這里干什么
Wilford's building a weapon. You know anything about that?
威爾福德在造武器 你知道這事嗎
I know he's up to something, but no.
我知道他在策劃什么 但不知道武器的事
Well, Ruth saw Javi working on it, so she wants to make contact with him.
魯絲看到哈維在制造那個武器 所以她想跟他取得聯系
I told you guys, Javi won't talk to me.
我告訴過你們了 哈維不愿跟我說話
He hasn't been the same since that dog attack.
自從被那只狗咬過之后 他整個人就變了
Well, we all got scars. It's Ruth's call. She wants to see him.
誰沒個傷疤呢  這是魯絲的決定 她想見他
Hitting the monitor does not tend to affect the satellite's geosync.
砸顯示器也不會讓衛星與地球同步
What it does do is make me feel better, but we're all falling out of orbit.
但能讓我感覺好受些 不過我們大家都不在狀態
How do you find a needle in a haystack?
本 我們要怎么在大海里撈到針呢
Thank God, it's only a haystack.
謝天謝地 只是一片大海而已
- You have any theories? - I have one theory.
-你有什么見解嗎  -只有一個
That he is following us?
他在跟蹤我們
That's a pretty good psychological assumption.
這一心理假設真不錯啊
If he is following us, we're back on the main line in a day or so.
我們將在一天左右回到主軌道 經過這里時
As we came through here, our satellite coverage improved.
我們的衛星覆蓋范圍會有所改善 如果他在跟蹤我們
Maybe we see him then.
或許我們就能探測到他
And he sees us?
他也能探測到我們
Your mum would be proud of how you handled the train yesterday.
你媽媽要是看到你昨天 駕馭列車時的表現 會很驕傲的
I don't really think so, Ben, but thank you.
我并不這么認為 本 不過謝謝你這么說
Alex, we found a survivor.
艾莉 我們找到了一個幸存者
Maybe we can hope for a miracle.
也許希望出現奇跡并無不可
She's gone, Ben.
她已經死了 本
It's all right.
我可以接受
Hey.
嘿
Tell me who she is.
跟我說說她是誰
At least tell me what you're looking for.
至少告訴我你在找什么
What did you find?
你找到了什么
Just, uh, in here.
就在這里
I've made it up for you.
我為你布置了一下
Josie. Josie.
喬西
It's all right. It'll all come back.
沒事 會慢慢熟練起來的
You all right?
你沒事吧
Hey.
嗨
How close you ever come to freezing to death?
你離被凍死最近的一次有多近
I guess no less than most of us.
跟多數人差不多吧
Is it like they say?
那經歷跟大家說的一樣嗎
Yeah.
是的
You start to relax. It goes warm.
你開始放松 開始覺得暖和
You see things.
會看到一些東西
Okay.
好吧
Like, uh, trees?
比如說樹
Dragon's blood tree. Grass.
龍血樹 青草
I could feel the sun.
我能感覺到陽光
It was the place we're looking for.
那是我們在找的地方
Well, I'm glad you came back 'cause it wasn't.
很高興你活過來了 因為那不是我們在找的地方
No, look, these trees only grow in the Gulf of Aden,
不 聽著 這種樹只在亞丁灣生長
right here in the middle of our Arabian warm spot.
亞丁灣就在阿拉伯暖點的中間
I'd never even heard of a dragon's blood tree before,
我以前從沒聽說過龍血樹
but I saw it.
可我卻看到了它
Are you saying you had a vision?
你是說你看到了未來
- I'm just telling you what happened. - You tell anyone else?
-我只是在告訴你當時發生的事 -你告訴過別人嗎
- No. - Good.
-沒有 -很好
Keep it on the rails.
保持正常狀態
You had a close call, something popped out of your memory.
你當時差點沒命了 所以記憶中的某些東西閃現了出來
Some tree you learned about in high school.
高中時學過的某種樹
Yeah. Yeah, you're probably right. Thanks.
是呀 你或許是對的 謝謝提點
Yeah. Okay.
嗯 好
Another day, another near-death experience, right?
和往常一樣 又經歷一次瀕死體驗 對嗎
Okay.
好
- Love you, buddy. - Yeah.
-我愛你 哥們 -嗯
We're on a different tack today, Kevin.
凱文 今天我們的攻勢與往日不同
A charm offensive.
我們要發起魅力攻勢
What do you think?
你覺得怎么樣
Too much red?
太紅了嗎
Never enough red, sir.
紅色永不嫌夠 先生
I agree.
我同意
- Why'd you say that? - Say what?
-你為什么要那么說  -說什么
What?
我說什么了
"Folger-Osweiller."
“弗爾杰-奧斯威勒”
I just said it. I didn't know he'd put it on the register.
我只是那么一說而已 沒想到他會記到登記簿上
Yeah, well, it's his wedding now.
是呀 這下他成了婚禮的主角
- I knew he'd do this. - So what?
-我就知道他會這么做 -那又怎樣
We get to be king and queen of everything for a day.
這一天 我們將會享受 國王和王后的待遇
He's using us, LJ.
他是在利用我們 LJ
He's investing in us.
他是在我們身上作投資
I would've been very happy with something small.
辦一場小小的儀式 我就很開心了
Sing you a song, a few of us. That wasn't on the table, was it?
給你唱首歌 就幾個朋友在場 但這是不可能的 對嗎
Yeah, because we don't have any friends.
沒錯 因為我們沒有朋友
I wanna be in a power couple. We could run this train one day.
我希望我們成為大腕夫婦 有一天我們可能會管理這列列車
- LJ, Jesus! - What?
-天啊 LJ  -怎么了
Old people keep dying off, there's barely any young people left.
年邁的人不斷死去 都快沒有年輕人了
And soon, we'll have to rule them.
很快 就得由我們來統領他們
It's our wedding day. Do you ever stop conniving?
這可是我們的婚禮啊 你就從不停止算計嗎
- Conniving is good. - Fine!
-算計是好事 -好吧
Connive away! It's too late to call it off now,
去算計吧 現在想取消已經太遲了
'cause Wilford would have my head out a port, wouldn't he?
因為提出取消 威爾福德就會 把我的腦袋凍掉 對嗎
Don't walk away from me!
別這樣甩手走開
Oz?
奧斯
Javi?
哈維
You can talk to me. No one is here.
你可以跟我說話的 這里沒有別人
Engineer, Wilford wants you down in First.
工程師 威爾福德要你去頭等車廂
But I'm on shift.
可我在上班呢
I don't know. That's what he wants, so put it on autopilot and off you go.
我不知道 他要你去的 所以設成自動駕駛 快去就是
You look beautiful.
你看上去很漂亮
- It's your big day. - Would you leave it?
今天是你的大日子
I don't care if it looks like shit. Just leave it.
你能別去管它了嗎
Oh, dear. I heard the bride might be blue, but blue in the face?
我不在乎它是否亂糟糟的 別去管它就是
Excuse me.
天啊 我聽說過新娘子會有婚前憂郁 不知道還會大發脾氣
Yes, that will be best, thank you.
-我先出去了 -好 那樣最好 謝謝
Now, now, here. Now, tell me what you fought about?
好了 來 告訴我你在為什么生氣
"You're always conniving." He thinks I'm selfish and I'm cruel.
“你總是在算計” 他覺得我又自私又冷酷
I have to be sometimes, don't I?
有時候我不得不那樣 不是嗎
It's why I wanted you in the Nightcar, LJ.
所以我才想讓你待在夜車上 LJ
You're a realist. You understand someone always gets hurt.
你是個現實主義者 你知道有人受傷是難免的事
Yes, it's like, I don't say it out loud, but c'est la vie.
就是 我雖然不會大聲說出來 但“這就是生活”
He also probably thinks I'm taking over the whole ceremony.
他或許還覺得 整場婚禮都被我接管了
Do you understand why your wedding is important to me?
你明白為什么 你們的婚禮對我很重要嗎
Helps keep everyone in line.
能幫你管束大家
Yes. They see there's only one way, the way I do things.
沒錯 他們會看到 只有一種辦事方法 就是我的方法
You see, on the train, the old laws and morality,
你看 在這列列車上 有一樣東西
- Loyalty. - That's right.
-忠誠 -沒錯
Loyalty to the train.
對列車的忠誠
Now, save the crocodile tears for the ceremony.
好了 你這假惺惺的眼淚 留著到婚禮上流吧
Make a show of it, for me.
為了我 好好表演一番
I will.
我會的
See you soon.
回頭見
Lovely spot for your wedding bed.
婚床放在這里很不錯呀
Thank you. We, uh, did it ourselves.
謝謝夸獎 是我們自己布置的
Come.
過來
Sit down. Come on.
坐 來啊
Young, tumultuous love, I know it well.
年輕激昂的愛情 我很熟悉
Well, the tumultuous part, not the young bit anymore.
我指的是激昂的部分 我已經不再年輕了
But LJ's upset.
不過 LJ不開心
Pre-wedding jitters.
是婚前緊張
We'll be fine. Yeah.
我們會沒事的 是的
Well, I am rather protective of her.
我對她有很強的保護意識
So I had a long look at Mr. Roche's personnel records,
所以 我好好查閱了一下 羅齊先生的人事記錄
and you were an opportunistic boy in blue.
你當制動員的時候 很會把握各種機會嘛
Well, ran a few side hustles. Yes, sir.
我經營過幾份副業 是的 先生
Ah, an entrepreneur with a vicious streak.
一個劣跡斑斑的企業家
Good qualities in a Nightcar manager.
這是當夜車經理的優良品質
play piano so beautifully.
卻能彈奏如此動聽的鋼琴曲
Part of you just yearns to be an artiste,
你心里有點渴望成為一名藝術家
warbling the saddest of songs.
顫聲吟唱最悲傷的歌曲
Well, I didn't grow up in what you'd call a creative environment.
我不是在所謂的 富有創造性的環境中長大的
You found your voice.
你表達了自己的心聲
Piano man, hmm?
鋼琴師
And his ginger wife behind the bar.
你那紅發妻子則負責吧臺
You're my team here.
你們是我的團隊
We understand that.
這點我們明白
We do.
真的
Your Brakeman shakedown move, remember?
你們制動員搜身的手法 還記得嗎
Squeeze mine too.
你也抓我的
Go on. Squeeze them.
來吧 抓吧
Harder.
用力點
Harder. Give them some basso profundo.
再用力點 用上所有的勁道
Now, what are your hands for, hmm?
好 你的雙手是用來干什么的
Crushing balls.
捏碎別人的蛋
And caressing your wife.
還要用來愛撫你的妻子
When that's done, by all means, tickle the ivories.
在那之后 你想怎么彈琴都行
Because you're very talented.
因為你非常有才華
I mean that.
這是真心話
Papers.
文件
Bag.
包
Mr. De la Torre.
德拉托爾先生
Just me.
是我
Long time no see.
好久不見了
You're on the other train.
你應該在另一列列車上呀
No, I've been here the whole time. I've been helping the passengers.
不 我一直都在這里 幫助乘客們
Doing my bit for our friends out there.
為我們在外面的朋友盡己所能
You shouldn't be here.
你不該在這里的
Oh, Javi.
哈維
The thing that you're working on back there, what is it? What does it do?
你在列車后部做的那個東西 它是什么 它能做什么
It's gonna stop Layton dead.
它能徹底阻止雷頓
- I need to go back to the dog, I'm sorry. - No, not yet.
-我得回狗那里去了 抱歉 -不 先別走
Tell me how it works.
你得告訴我它是怎么運作的
- No. No! No! - Javi? Javi!
-不  -哈維 哈維
Gorgeous.
你美極了
Welcome, brave passengers, workers, all now.
歡迎 勇敢的乘客們 工人們 及其他所有人
It's my great pleasure to pause our labors,
我很高興大家能暫停手頭的工作
and spend time in union.
花點時間團聚在一起
The union today by marriage,
今天我們匯聚一堂 是為了慶祝
of Lilah Folger Junior and John Christopher Osweiller.
小萊拉弗爾杰 和約翰克里斯多夫奧斯威勒喜結良緣
I know these have been cold miles of deprivation.
我知道 最近這段行程 非常寒冷 供給不足
And discipline is harsh.
紀律嚴酷
You've paid in frostbite,
你們都得了凍瘡
and loved ones lost to influenza. May they rest in peace.
所愛的人因流感而喪生 愿他們安息
So it's time we celebrate a win, isn't it?
所以 該是慶祝勝利的時候了 不是嗎
Old World matrimony.
傳統的婚姻
Everyone, fill a glass. There's enough for every soul.
各位 把酒杯倒滿 我們有足夠的酒 大家都有份
Extra hot food too.
還有額外的熱餐
- I'll be back. - Okay.
-我去去就回 -好
Raise a glass up and down our train for Lilah and John.
讓全車上下 都為萊拉和約翰舉起酒杯吧
Come on. Cheers.
來吧 干杯
Everyone now.
現在 各位
To our unbreakable pact with the train.
再敬我們與列車牢不可破的協議
To loyalty
敬忠誠
and your contract with me.
以及你們與我的約定
To survive.
生存
Wilford! Wilford!
威爾福德
Sounds like an electromagnetic pulse weapon.
聽上去像是一種電磁脈沖武器
Never actually seen one before.
我從來沒有真正見過
- But you do know how it works? - Yeah.
-但你知道它的運作原理吧  -知道
It sends out an electromagnetic pulse killing the electronics on Snowpiercer,
它能發出電磁脈沖 破壞雪國列車上的所有電子設備
leaving Layton dead in the water.
讓雷頓的列車無法前進
So while this wedding is happening, let's try and make it not do that.
那趁著這場婚禮 我們來設法阻止那種情況發生
- You got a manual?
有操作手冊嗎
- Come on, Lights.
拜托 光明
I told the lady you're good at this kind of thing.
我跟魯絲說你很擅長這類活兒
Disarming EMPs?
解除電磁脈沖武器
Yeah.
是呀
What?
干嗎
Where you going, Javi?
哈維 你要去哪兒
- Back to the dog. - Ah-ah.
回狗那里去
Where are you coming from?
你剛才去哪兒了
Final data collection.
收集最后一套數據
Can I go?
我能走了嗎
Come with me.
跟我來
Follow me.
跟著我
You too.
你也是
Now, I ask you to take the sacred steps
現在 我要你們完成
in union with the Eternal Engine.
與永恒機車相結合的神圣儀式
These four steps represent the path humanity has taken.
這四步代表了人類所經歷的歷程
From grass
從青草
to ice.
到寒冰
- From ice to steel. - From ice to steel.
-從寒冰到鋼鐵 -從寒冰到鋼鐵
of the Eternal Engine.
永恒機車的燈光
Anyone come through here?
有人來過這里嗎
That dog-faced engineer's here all the time.
那個被狗咬了臉的工程師常來這里
But he's in and out.
不過他很快就會出來
Well, we'll check it anyway.
我們還是要進去看看
Wouldn't this wedding be a great distraction for the enemy?
敵人會覺得這場婚禮 是他們行動的好時機 不是嗎
I have no idea how to disarm this thing.
我完全不知道要怎么解除這玩意兒
Just start messing with it.
你就各處擺弄一下唄
- That's your plan? - You're my plan.
-這就是你的計劃  -你才是我的計劃
Jackboots and teal coming!
軍靴和待客部的人來了
- What? - They'll pin us back here. Let's go.
-什么  -我們會被困在這里的 快離開
We gotta go. Let's go.
我們得走了 快走
- Come on. - No. You need to keep working on it.
-來呀 -不行 你們得繼續解除武器
What are you gonna do?
你打算干什么
I'll need to run interference or we're all stuck back here.
我得去干擾他們 否則大家都會被困在這里
They won't keep coming if they see me.
如果他們看到了我 就不會進到這里來
Just disable it, and give Layton a fighting chance.
只管解除這武器 給雷頓一個戰斗機會
- Ruth-- - That is an order, Mr. Pike.
-魯絲… -派克先生 這是命令
You're in charge now.
現在由你來負責了
I believe in you.
我信任你
Congratulations.
恭喜啊
That's nice.
真不錯
You.
是你
Yes, Kevin. It's me.
沒錯 凱文 是我
The one you've been looking for all this time.
你一直以來都在找的人
Running around like a chicken with your head cut off.
你像只沒頭蒼蠅一樣到處瞎找
I'm surrendering.
現在我來投降了
I'm cold and I'm starving. So, come on.
我又冷又餓 所以 動手吧
You get to be the hero without ever lifting a finger.
不費吹灰之力 你就能當上英雄了
Take her.
把她帶走
There were 34 of us to start,
最初我們有34個人
eking it out on the plant's residual power.
依靠核電站的剩余電力竭力維持
Korean scientists,
都是韓國科學家
foreign nuclear technicians like me.
以及像我這樣的外國核技術人員
Some of our families too.
還有我們的一些家人
Marauders killed about half of us before they died out. And then--
掠奪者死光之前 殺死了我們大約一半的人 然后…
Marauders?
掠奪者
And then the cold or radiation poisoning took the rest of us.
然后嚴寒或輻射中毒 奪走了其余人的性命
My nephew, he was 15 years old.
我侄子當時是15歲
He was the last to go.
他是最后一個死的
He had thyroid cancer.
他得了甲狀腺癌
By the end, he was begging me to kill him.
到最后 他在求我把他殺了
That was about four years ago.
那是大約四年前的事了
I lost time.
我就沒有了時間的概念
I stopped hoping, stopped thinking.
不再抱有希望 不再去想
It's like someone other than me lived down there.
除了我之外還有其他人住在那下面
Then I turned my eyes on you.
然后我看見了你
I hate to tell you this,
我很抱歉地告訴你
but humankind hasn't exactly evolved in your absence.
在你與世隔絕期間 人類并沒怎么進化
You pushed past what was safe, even sane, to rescue me.
你甘冒生命危險 甚至不顧理智 就為了救我
Why?
為什么
I'm just glad I did.
我很高興自己那么做了
We're still basically blind.
我們還是基本沒有信號
We had picture last time we came out here.
我們上次到這里時還有衛星圖像的
The satellites continue to degrade. - Options?
-衛星信號在持續減弱 -說說其他選擇
- Wait, there's options?
等等 我們有其他選擇
We go back directly to the main line,
我們直接回到主軌道上
where we either see physical signs they're in front of us,
到時候 如果他們在我們前面 我們就會看到跡象
or we know they're behind us.
不然 我們就知道他們在后面
Or we parallel the main line,
或者我們可以與主軌道平行前進
hoping the signal improves enough so we can glimpse them on the sat.
希望信號會變好 能讓我們在衛星圖像上探測到他們
- Second route. - Roger that.
-選第二個方法 -遵命
And, um, you picked that based on what?
你剛才那樣決定的依據是什么
Another vision?
又看到了未來
No, I mean, there's gotta be more options off the main line, right?
不是 不上主軌道 我們會有更多選擇的余地 對嗎
Yeah.
對
She sacrificed for us. So now, we gotta kill this thing.
她為我們犧牲了自己 所以現在我們得解除這玩意兒
- Okay? - The laptop patch is in here.
-好嗎  -這是筆記本電腦的連接口
So we can't hack the software.
所以沒法黑入它的軟件
Maybe we can disrupt the power supply, mess with it.
也許我們可以中斷電源 擾亂它的供電
Looks like an arming sequence.
這好像是裝載程序面板
- It's live. - Oh, shit!
-它被激活了 -糟糕
- I think it's at full pulse. - I can see that.
-我覺得它處于全脈沖狀態 -是 我看到了
I can't turn it down.
我沒法把它關了
It's not stopping.
停不下來
I knew it had to be someone with acumen for rail logistics.
我早知道會是一個 對鐵路后勤具有敏銳洞察力的人
But to be honest, I'm more impressed with how low you went
但老實說 更令我欽佩的是
to grovel it out in the bowels.
你居然會如此屈尊 跟末等人混在一起
Well, I do try not to disappoint, sir.
我在盡量不辜負期望 先生
If you'd only stayed loyal.
如果你能保持忠誠該多好
I am loyal.
我是忠誠的
To something bigger than you. You've got it all wrong, Mr. Wilford.
我的忠誠給了比你更重要的東西 威爾福德先生 你全搞錯了
I hear that all the time, and then I win.
這話我一直聽到 但我還是贏了
Winning isn't leading.
贏和領導是兩回事
Loyalty isn't enough on its own.
光有忠誠還不夠
It has to come with love. And not the kind that you feed off.
還需要有愛 不是你享受的那種敬畏之愛
Unconditional love. Sacrifice, for each and every passenger.
而是無條件的愛 愿為每一個乘客犧牲
- Oh, God! - You can't ignore love.
-老天  -你不能忽視愛的力量
You can't predict it either.
你也無法預測它的力量
We gotta get this thing out that door.
好吧 我們得把這玩意兒 送出那扇門去
Year two rebellion.
第二年那場叛亂
They sealed the subtrain doors on us, but we compromised the hinges.
他們封了通勤車的門不讓我們上 但我們弄壞了鉸鏈
Go.
快去
Here.
在這里
Strong Boy, get it ready.
強壯男孩 準備好
Okay. Clear. Come on.
好 解除了 來吧
Let's go.
動手吧
Ready!
準備好了
They're preparing the port for you now.
他們此刻正在為你準備門洞
I'll make sure they mount the cuff nice and high
我會確保他們把臂銬放高夾緊
where prosthetics are impossible.
讓你將來沒法裝假肢
Wouldn't wear one anyway.
反正我也不會戴假肢
Come on. You got it?
來吧 你好了嗎
Okay, run. Run, sister, run.
好 快跑 姐妹 快跑
Go.
快走
The irony is, I built the ports in as an idle threat.
諷刺的是 我當初建門洞 只是一種虛聲恫嚇
Never expected to use them.
從沒想過要使用它們
You did.
而你卻用了
Thirteen times.
13次
I'll pay my penance.
我愿意贖罪
You can have my arm.
把我的手臂凍掉吧
- Whoa. - Whoa.
我很好奇那會是什么
I wonder, what on earth could that be?
是電磁波
Electromagnetic?
正在三角定位
Triangulating.
這是特征痕跡 一定是他們
Well, that's the signature. It's gotta be them.
沒錯 是他們
Yes, it is. Five hundred and twenty kilometers west.
在我們西側520公里處
They're on the main line.
他們在主軌道上
That's a lot better than seeing them on sat.
這比在衛星圖像上找到他們強多了
Yeah? So it means Wilford can't see us.
是嗎 也就是說威爾福德看不到我們
We got the drop on him.
我們比他有優勢
- Well, Wilford hates surprises. - Good.
-威爾福德討厭意外之事 -很好
Let's go give him one.
我們去給他一個“驚喜”
I built something for you.
我為你們做了一樣東西
Something that would have saved countless lives.
一樣本可以挽救無數性命的東西
We could have snuffed out Layton's pirate train
我們本可以不費一顆彈藥
without firing a shot.
就毀掉雷頓的強盜列車
Now, thanks to a rat
如今 就因為一個
found hiding in the pipes,
躲在管道中的叛徒
when this war comes,
這場戰爭爆發時
you're all going to bleed.
你們將會有傷亡
It's back to broadswords and shields because of you.
都因為你 這場戰爭 又將回到原始的打斗方法
Ready when you are, sir.
先生 好了 隨時可以行刑
Let's get it bloody off then.
那就凍斷它吧
They're back. They're back.
他們回來了
- Battle stations! - Let's go!
-去戰斗崗位  -快走
Battle stations, you dogs!
去戰斗崗位 狗崽子們
Come on!
快啊